Boston Dispensary Records MS214
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- Treasurer records, 1796 -- 1916; MS214.014
  - Receipts - payment to stockbroker and receipts for railroad stock, 1860 -- 1862; MS214.014.024.00132 (Box 24, Folder 132)
  - U.S. Government - IRS Form, 1864; MS214.014.024.00133 (Box 24, Folder 133)
  - City of Boston - Property Taxes, 1858 -- 1877; MS214.014.024.00134 (Box 24, Folder 134)
  - Treasurer - Salary - receipts, 1860; MS214.014.024.00135 (Box 24, Folder 135)
  - Dentist - Receipts for services, 1863; MS214.014.024.00136 (Box 24, Folder 136)
  - Receipts - Dental Department - Physician's Fees, 1877 -- 1879; MS214.014.024.00137 (Box 24, Folder 137)
  - Dr. Jacob Bigelow - Application and Recommendation, 1811; MS214.014.024.00138 (Box 24, Folder 138)
  - Dr. Francis Gray, Recommendation, 1834; MS214.014.024.00139 (Box 24, Folder 139)
  - J. Fogg, reappointment, 1833; MS214.014.024.00140 (Box 24, Folder 140)
  - Letter of Resignation, Dr. Wheeler resigns under charges of abuse levied by female patient, 1838; MS214.014.024.00141 (Box 24, Folder 141)
  - Dr. A. Stone, Application, 1842; MS214.014.024.00142 (Box 24, Folder 142)
  - Dr. J.H.W. Lane, Resignation and observation recandidates for charity, 1843; MS214.014.024.00143 (Box 24, Folder 143)
  - Dr. Edward Hale, Recommendation, 1843; MS214.014.024.00144 (Box 24, Folder 144)
  - Dr. Andrew Alexander, Application, 1844; MS214.014.024.00145 (Box 24, Folder 145)
  - Dr. Thompson, recommendation (by O.W. Holmes), 1843; MS214.014.024.00146 (Box 24, Folder 146)
  - Dr. Moses Wold, Application and Recommendation (by O.W. Holmes), 1847; MS214.014.024.00147 (Box 24, Folder 147)
  - James Stone, recommendation by O.W. Holmes, 1847; MS214.014.024.00148 (Box 24, Folder 148)
  - Correspondence - Dr. E.B. Moore, re: Housing, 1848; MS214.014.024.00149 (Box 24, Folder 149)
  - Dr. H.W. Adams, Recommendation by Dr. Jacob Bigelow, 1852; MS214.014.024.00150 (Box 24, Folder 150)
  - Drs. Ellis and Adams, Recommendation (by R. Lawrence), 1858; MS214.014.024.00151 (Box 24, Folder 151)
  - Henry Robey - Letter, re: Clinical Work, 1898; MS214.014.024.00152 (Box 24, Folder 152)
  - Account book, 1847-1872; MS214.014.026.00001 (Box 20-23, 26, Box 26)
  - Account book, 1872 -- 1894; MS214.014.019.00001 (Box 19)
    Material is in poor condition. Handle with care.
  - Account book, 1895 -- 1921; MS214.014.026.00002 (Box 20-23, 26, Box 26)
- District Physician records, 1797 -- 1931; MS214.015
  - District reports, 1797 -- 1798; MS214.015.017.00050 (Box 17, Folder 50)
  - District reports, 1799 -- 1800; MS214.015.017.00051 (Box 17, Folder 51)
  - District reports, 1802 -- 1803; MS214.015.017.00052 (Box 17, Folder 52)
  - District reports, 1805; MS214.015.017.00053 (Box 17, Folder 53)
  - District reports, 1810 -- 1811; MS214.015.017.00054 (Box 17, Folder 54)
  - District reports, 1813; MS214.015.017.00055 (Box 17, Folder 55)
  - District reports, 1817; MS214.015.017.00056 (Box 17, Folder 56)
  - District reports, 1817 -- 1818; MS214.015.017.00057 (Box 17, Folder 57)
  - District reports, 1819 -- 1820; MS214.015.017.00058 (Box 17, Folder 58)
  - District reports, 1822; MS214.015.017.00059 (Box 17, Folder 59)
  - District reports, 1823; MS214.015.017.00060 (Box 17, Folder 60)
  - District reports, 1824; MS214.015.017.00061 (Box 17, Folder 61)
  - District reports, 1824 -- 1825; MS214.015.017.00062 (Box 17, Folder 62)
  - District reports, 1825 -- 1826; MS214.015.017.00063 (Box 17, Folder 63)
  - District reports, 1826; MS214.015.017.00064 (Box 17, Folder 64)
  - District reports, 1829; MS214.015.017.00065 (Box 17, Folder 65)
  - District reports, 1829 -- 1830; MS214.015.017.00066 (Box 17, Folder 66)
  - District reports, 1830; MS214.015.017.00067 (Box 17, Folder 67)
  - District reports on abuse of charity by patients, 1830; MS214.015.017.00068 (Box 17, Folder 68)
  - District reports, 1830 -- 1831; MS214.015.017.00069 (Box 17, Folder 69)
  - Annual abstracts of patients, 1830; MS214.015.017.00070 (Box 17, Folder 70)
  - District report, summary of intemperance, 1831; MS214.015.017.00071 (Box 17, Folder 71)
  - District report, note on ethnic identities and profession of patients, 1831 -- 1832; MS214.015.017.00072 (Box 17, Folder 72)
  - District report, nymphomania, 1831 -- 1832; MS214.015.017.00073 (Box 17, Folder 73)
  - District report, social classification of patients, 1832; MS214.015.017.00074 (Box 17, Folder 74)
  - District report, social classification of patients, 1832; MS214.015.017.00075 (Box 17, Folder 75)
  - District report, note on intemperance among patients, 1833; MS214.015.017.00076 (Box 17, Folder 76)
  - Notice of annual board meeting, 1823; MS214.015.017.00077 (Box 17, Folder 77)
  - Annual report and abstracts with notice of meeting, 1824; MS214.015.017.00078 (Box 17, Folder 78)
  - Annual report and abstract with circular letter, 1828; MS214.015.017.00079 (Box 17, Folder 79)
  - Annual report and notice of meeting with abstract on patients, 1830; MS214.015.017.00080 (Box 17, Folder 80)
  - Annual report and abstract with notice of meeting, 1832; MS214.015.017.00081 (Box 17, Folder 81)
  - Annual report and notice of meeting, 1836; MS214.015.017.00082 (Box 17, Folder 82)
  - Annual abstracts of patients, 1838 -- 1842; MS214.015.017.00083 (Box 17, Folder 83)
  - Annual report and abstracts of patients, 1843 -- 1846; MS214.015.017.00084 (Box 17, Folder 84)
  - Annual report and abstracts of district physicians, 1848 -- 1849; MS214.015.017.00085 (Box 17, Folder 85)
  - Annual abstracts of patients with notice of meeting, 1850 -- 1855; MS214.015.017.00086 (Box 17, Folder 86)
  - District report, 1873 -- 1878; MS214.015.017.00087 (Box 17, Folder 87)
  - Medical staff list, 1857; MS214.015.017.00088 (Box 17, Folder 88)
  - Physicians fees, Dr. John Fleet, 1796 -- 1802; MS214.015.017.00089 (Box 17, Folder 89)
  - Physicians fees, bill for nurse and electrical machine, 1838; MS214.015.017.00090 (Box 17, Folder 90)
  - Physicians fees, 1848 -- 1859; MS214.015.017.00091 (Box 17, Folder 91)
  - Physicians fees, 1860 -- 1868; MS214.015.017.00092 (Box 17, Folder 92)
  - Physicians fees and receipts, 1871 -- 1876; MS214.015.017.00093 (Box 17, Folder 93)
  - Physicians fees, 1877 -- 1879; MS214.015.017.00094 (Box 17, Folder 94)
  - Physicians fees, 1880 -- 1881; MS214.015.017.00095 (Box 17, Folder 95)
  - Dr. Jacob Gates, recommendation, 1818; MS214.015.017.00096 (Box 17, Folder 96)
  - Dr. Asa Ballards, resignation, 1810; MS214.015.017.00097 (Box 17, Folder 97)
  - Dr. I. Revere, recommendation and resignation, 1811 -- 1816; MS214.015.017.00098 (Box 17, Folder 98)
  - Dr. David Osgood, recommendation, 1819; MS214.015.017.00099 (Box 17, Folder 99)
  - Dr. J. B. Brown, recommendation, 1814; MS214.015.017.00100 (Box 17, Folder 100)
  - Dr. Niles, recommendation, 1817; MS214.015.017.00101 (Box 17, Folder 101)
  - Dr. John Ware, recommendation, 1817; MS214.015.017.00102 (Box 17, Folder 102)
  - Dr. J. D. Townsend, application, 1819; MS214.015.017.00103 (Box 17, Folder 103)
  - Dr. Gamaliel Bradford, application, recommendation, and resignation, 1819 -- 1821; MS214.015.017.00104 (Box 17, Folder 104)
  - Dr. Asa Buckman, resignation, 1819; MS214.015.017.00105 (Box 17, Folder 105)
  - Dr. Sammuel Morrill, recommendation, 1824; MS214.015.017.00106 (Box 17, Folder 106)
  - Dr. J. Greely Stevenson, application and recommendation, 1826; MS214.015.017.00107 (Box 17, Folder 107)
  - Dr. J. H. Lane, recommendation, 1826; MS214.015.017.00108 (Box 17, Folder 108)
  - Dr. Arthur Lincoln, recommendation, 1827; MS214.015.017.00109 (Box 17, Folder 109)
  - Dr. Phineas Crane, recommendation, 1828; MS214.015.017.00110 (Box 17, Folder 110)
  - Dr. Francis Higginson, recommendation and resignation, 1829 -- 1830; MS214.015.017.00111 (Box 17, Folder 111)
  - Dr. Edar Davenport, recommendation, 1831; MS214.015.017.00112 (Box 17, Folder 112)
  - Dr. John B. S. Jackson, recommendation, 1831; MS214.015.017.00113 (Box 17, Folder 113)
  - Dr. Charles Putnam, recommendation, 1834; MS214.015.017.00114 (Box 17, Folder 114)
  - Dr. J. C. Chickening, application and recommendation, 1834; MS214.015.017.00115 (Box 17, Folder 115)
  - Dr. O. W. Holmes, recommendation, 1839; MS214.015.017.00116 (Box 17, Folder 116)
  - Dr. William Bouditch, reappointment and resignation, 1836; MS214.015.017.00117 (Box 17, Folder 117)
  - Dr. Warren Whitman, recommendation, 1836; MS214.015.017.00118 (Box 17, Folder 118)
  - Dr. William Dwight, resignation, 1836; MS214.015.017.00119 (Box 17, Folder 119)
  - Dr. Stocker, district change correspondence, 1837; MS214.015.017.00120 (Box 17, Folder 120)
  - Dr. Charles S. Ware, recommendation, 1837; MS214.015.017.00121 (Box 17, Folder 121)
  - Dr. Sammuel Parkman, recommendation, 1838; MS214.015.017.00122 (Box 17, Folder 122)
  - Dr. Sammuel Wiggleworth, application, 1838; MS214.015.017.00123 (Box 17, Folder 123)
  - Dr. B. B. Appleton, recommendation, 1839; MS214.015.017.00124 (Box 17, Folder 124)
  - Dr. Thomas M. Brewer, resignation, 1840; MS214.015.017.00125 (Box 17, Folder 125)
  - Dr. William Brigga, recommendation, 1841; MS214.015.017.00126 (Box 17, Folder 126)
  - Dr. Francis Tuckerman, resignation and observations, 1841; MS214.015.017.00127 (Box 17, Folder 127)
  - Dr. Sammuel Cabot Jr., application and district reassignment correspondence, 1841 -- 1842; MS214.015.017.00128 (Box 17, Folder 128)
  - Dr. E. Becker, resignation and observations on abuse of charity and Irish patients, 1841; MS214.015.017.00129 (Box 17, Folder 129)
  - Dr. William A. Dexter, recommendation, 1842; MS214.015.017.00130 (Box 17, Folder 130)
  - Dr. Cobanon Russell, recommendation, 1844; MS214.015.017.00131 (Box 17, Folder 131)
  - Dr. Henry Thayer, application, recommendations, resignation, and observations, 1844 -- 1845; MS214.015.017.00132 (Box 17, Folder 132)
  - Dr. William E. Townsend, recommendation, 1845; MS214.015.017.00133 (Box 17, Folder 133)
  - Dr. Carter, recommendation, 1845; MS214.015.017.00134 (Box 17, Folder 134)
  - Dr. Isaac Winslow, resignation, 1845; MS214.015.017.00135 (Box 17, Folder 135)
  - Dr. Kneeland, recommendation, 1845; MS214.015.017.00136 (Box 17, Folder 136)
  - Dr. George Derby, application and recommendation, 1845 -- 1846; MS214.015.017.00137 (Box 17, Folder 137)
  - Dr. Edward Oliver, application, 1845; MS214.015.017.00138 (Box 17, Folder 138)
  - Dr. E. P. Wells, resignation, 1846; MS214.015.017.00139 (Box 17, Folder 139)
  - Dr. Francis Minot, application and resignation, 1847 -- 1851; MS214.015.017.00140 (Box 17, Folder 140)
  - Dr. John B. Alley, application and recommendation, 1850; MS214.015.017.00141 (Box 17, Folder 141)
  - Dr. George B. Baily, recommendation, 1850; MS214.015.017.00142 (Box 17, Folder 142)
  - Dr. William Bowen Morris, application, 1850; MS214.015.017.00143 (Box 17, Folder 143)
  - Dr. Luther Parks Jr., observations regarding Irish Catholics and other patients, 1850; MS214.015.017.00144 (Box 17, Folder 144)
  - Dr. Joshua Sharpe, resignation, 1850; MS214.015.017.00145 (Box 17, Folder 145)
  - Dr. Algerman Coolidge, application and resignation, 1851 -- 1854; MS214.015.017.00146 (Box 17, Folder 146)
  - Dr. A. Hodges, recommendation, 1852; MS214.015.017.00147 (Box 17, Folder 147)
  - Dr. John C. York, recommendation, 1852; MS214.015.017.00148 (Box 17, Folder 148)
  - Dr. George Tucker, resignation, 1855; MS214.015.017.00149 (Box 17, Folder 149)
  - Dr. C. W. Moore, recommendation and resignation, 1854 -- 1857; MS214.015.017.00150 (Box 17, Folder 150)
  - Dr. David W. Cheerer, application and recommendation, 1858; MS214.015.017.00151 (Box 17, Folder 151)
  - Dr. Samuel Green, application, 1858; MS214.015.017.00152 (Box 17, Folder 152)
  - Dr. H. Osgood, recommendation, 1858; MS214.015.017.00153 (Box 17, Folder 153)
  - Dr. J. B. Treadwell, resignation, 1861; MS214.015.017.00154 (Box 17, Folder 154)
  - Dr. Eldridge Cutler, application, 1870; MS214.015.017.00155 (Box 17, Folder 155)
  - Dr. Francis D. Brown, application, 1870; MS214.015.017.00156 (Box 17, Folder 156)
  - Dr. Appell, recommendation, 1879; MS214.015.017.00157 (Box 17, Folder 157)
- Apothecary records, 1798 -- 1883; MS214.016
  - Accounts of Robert Fennelly, 1803; MS214.016.017.00158 (Box 17, Folder 158)
  - Accounts of Thomas Bartlett, 1798 -- 1800; MS214.016.017.00159 (Box 17, Folder 159)
  - Report of Dr. Robert Fennelly with list of patients, doctors, and subscribers, 1804 -- 1805; MS214.016.017.00160 (Box 17, Folder 160)
  - Persons recommended to the Boston Dispensary "Southern District", 1806; MS214.016.017.00161 (Box 17, Folder 161)
  - List of patients, 1807 -- 1808; MS214.016.017.00162 (Box 17, Folder 162)
  - Bills, 1807 -- 1808; MS214.016.017.00163 (Box 17, Folder 163)
  - Accounts of W.B. White, 1809; MS214.016.017.00164 (Box 17, Folder 164)
  - Bills of Dr. Bartlett and Dr. Thayer, 1803; MS214.016.017.00165 (Box 17, Folder 165)
  - List of patients, 1809; MS214.016.017.00166 (Box 17, Folder 166)
  - List of patients, 1810; MS214.016.017.00167 (Box 17, Folder 167)
  - List of patients, Dr. Bartlett and Dr. Smith, 1810 -- 1811; MS214.016.017.00168 (Box 17, Folder 168)
  - Accounts, 1811 -- 1812; MS214.016.017.00169 (Box 17, Folder 169)
  - Reports, 1813; MS214.016.017.00170 (Box 17, Folder 170)
  - Accounts, 1813 -- 1814; MS214.016.017.00171 (Box 17, Folder 171)
  - Thomas Wakefield, application, 1815; MS214.016.017.00172 (Box 17, Folder 172)
  - Bills, 1815 -- 1817; MS214.016.017.00173 (Box 17, Folder 173)
  - Bill, Dr. William White, 1818; MS214.016.017.00174 (Box 17, Folder 174)
  - Request for greater compensation, Drs. Fennelly, White, and Wakefield, 1818; MS214.016.017.00175 (Box 17, Folder 175)
  - List of patients, 1818; MS214.016.017.00176 (Box 17, Folder 176)
  - Accounts, 1819 -- 1821; MS214.016.017.00177 (Box 17, Folder 177)
  - Account of Samuel Clark with record of medicines dispenced, 1823; MS214.016.017.00178 (Box 17, Folder 178)
  - List of patients, 1824; MS214.016.017.00179 (Box 17, Folder 179)
  - Account of Samuel Clark, 1824; MS214.016.017.00180 (Box 17, Folder 180)
  - Reports, 1825; MS214.016.017.00181 (Box 17, Folder 181)
  - Account of Samuel Clark, 1827; MS214.016.017.00182 (Box 17, Folder 182)
  - Accounts and bills, 1830 -- 1833; MS214.016.017.00183 (Box 17, Folder 183)
  - List of patients, 1831; MS214.016.017.00184 (Box 17, Folder 184)
  - List of certificates (patients, subscribers, and doctors), 1831; MS214.016.017.00185 (Box 17, Folder 185)
  - Accounts, 1833 -- 1837; MS214.016.017.00186 (Box 17, Folder 186)
  - Report of Committee to Examine Apothecary's Accounts, 1847 -- 1848; MS214.016.017.00187 (Box 17, Folder 187)
  - Accounts, 1849 -- 1851; MS214.016.017.00188 (Box 17, Folder 188)
  - Applications for position as central apothecary and agreement with the Board, 1839; MS214.016.017.00189 (Box 17, Folder 189)
  - Reports, 1856; MS214.016.017.00190 (Box 17, Folder 190)
  - Inventory of stock and furnishings, 1856; MS214.016.017.00191 (Box 17, Folder 191)
  - C.W. Moore, receipts for salary, 1856 -- 1857; MS214.016.017.00192 (Box 17, Folder 192)
  - Account of Emory Souther, 1857; MS214.016.017.00193 (Box 17, Folder 193)
  - Account of Anson N. Lincoln, 1857; MS214.016.017.00194 (Box 17, Folder 194)
  - Accounts of Redford, Campbell, and W.P. Howard, 1857; MS214.016.017.00195 (Box 17, Folder 195)
  - Account of Charles Moore, 1857; MS214.016.017.00196 (Box 17, Folder 196)
  - Correspondence, Charles Moore, 1857; MS214.016.017.00197 (Box 17, Folder 197)
  - Report of R. Kent, 1857; MS214.016.017.00198 (Box 17, Folder 198)
  - Accounts, 1858; MS214.016.017.00199 (Box 17, Folder 199)
  - Drug price list, 1858; MS214.016.017.00200 (Box 17, Folder 200)
  - Medical formulary for U.S. Dispensatory, 1862; MS214.016.017.00201 (Box 17, Folder 201)
  - Druggist's invoices, 1845 -- 1849; MS214.016.017.00202 (Box 17, Folder 202)
  - Bill for scarification, 1844; MS214.016.017.00203 (Box 17, Folder 203)
  - Grocer's invoices, 1848; MS214.016.017.00204 (Box 17, Folder 204)
  - Chemistry book receipt, 1848; MS214.016.017.00205 (Box 17, Folder 205)
  - Bill for ear leeches, 1850 -- 1855; MS214.016.017.00206 (Box 17, Folder 206)
  - Vintner's bills, 1850 -- 1854; MS214.016.017.00207 (Box 17, Folder 207)
  - Groceries and dry goods receipts, 1854 -- 1855; MS214.016.017.00208 (Box 17, Folder 208)
  - Wholesale druggist's receipts, 1854 -- 1857; MS214.016.017.00209 (Box 17, Folder 209)
  - Bills for leeches, 1847 -- 1848; MS214.016.017.00210 (Box 17, Folder 210)
  - Bills for leeches, 1859 -- 1861; MS214.016.017.00211 (Box 17, Folder 211)
  - Receipts for services, 1860 -- 1868; MS214.016.017.00212 (Box 17, Folder 212)
  - Druggist's invoices, 1862 -- 1867; MS214.016.017.00213 (Box 17, Folder 213)
  - Grocer's invoices, 1866; MS214.016.017.00214 (Box 17, Folder 214)
  - Druggist's invoices, Reed and Cutler, 1867 -- 1869; MS214.016.017.00215 (Box 17, Folder 215)
  - Receipts for salary, Frank Clark, 1870; MS214.016.017.00216 (Box 17, Folder 216)
  - Druggist's invoices, 1870 -- 1876; MS214.016.017.00217 (Box 17, Folder 217)
  - Receipt for "U.S. Pharmacoepia" (book), 1877; MS214.016.017.00218 (Box 17, Folder 218)
  - Receipts for salary, John Kelly, 1878; MS214.016.017.00219 (Box 17, Folder 219)
  - Druggist's invoices, 1877 -- 1879; MS214.016.017.00220 (Box 17, Folder 220)
  - Druggist's invoices, 1880 -- 1883; MS214.016.017.00221 (Box 17, Folder 221)
  - Vintner's accounts, 1813 -- 1816; MS214.016.017.00222 (Box 17, Folder 222)
  - Vintner's accounts, 1818; MS214.016.017.00223 (Box 17, Folder 223)
  - Vintner's invoices, 1846 -- 1847; MS214.016.017.00224 (Box 17, Folder 224)
  - Vintner's invoices, 1860 -- 1862; MS214.016.017.00225 (Box 17, Folder 225)
  - Vintner's bills, 1874 -- 1877; MS214.016.017.00226 (Box 17, Folder 226)
- Memorabilia and miscellaneous, 1795 -- 1966; MS214.017
  Personnel records are restricted for 75 years from the date of creation.
  Materials in this series were transferred to DCA by the Francis A. Countway Library of Medicine in August 2016, and June 2017: accession MS-2018-003.
  - Scrapbook and miscellaneous records, 1795 -- 1979; MS214.017.025 (Box 25)
    Accruals
    In July 2017 Records and Accessioning Archivist Leah Edelman added one folder to this box: Countway Library ready reference file, accession MS-2018-003. This folder includes the Centennial Report of the Boston Dispensary, 1796-1897; a brochure titled Since 1796: A tradition of helping; a thesis titled The Boston Dispensary: A Mirror of Changing Conceptions of Charity and Attitudes Towards the Poor, 1796-1858; the Massachusetts Physician, Volume 37, February 1978 (includes an article about the Dispensary); and a Boston Globe article about the Dispensary from 12/4/1977.
  - Scrapbook, 1900 -- 1907; MS214.017.020.00001 (Box 20-23, 26, Volume 1, Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, 1911 -- 1913; MS214.017.020.00002 (Box 20-23, 26, Volume 2, Box 20)
  - Scrapbook, 1913 -- 1923; MS214.017.021.001 (Box 20-23, 26, Volume 1, Box 1)
  - Fundraising campaign scrapbook, 1921; MS214.017.022.00001 (Box 20-23, 26, Volume 1, Box 22)
    Item is fragile. Please use under supervision of an archivist.
  - Scrapbook, 1923 -- 1927; MS214.017.023.00001 (Box 20-23, 26, Volume 1, Box 23)